<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>

    <string name="home_map"> Mappa </string>
    <string name="home_monuments"> Monumenti </string>
    <string name="cw_read_more"> Mostra tutto </string>
    <string name="go_monument"> Vai al momunmento </string>
    <string name="cw_hide_read_more"> Riduci </string>

    <string-array name="descriptions">
        <item>
               "This Bastion, one of the smallest sixteenth-century bulwarks, was dedicated to San Giorgio,
               protector of the castellan. Half-sinked by the 1669 eruptions, the Bastion was found
               during excavations carried out between the end Suca of the eighteenth-century and the beginning of the
               nineteenth-century, but it then got forgotten and overwhelmed by the new factories.
               Today, it still appears covered by lava and victim of any sort of vandalism,
               being it in a neighborhood at social risk."

        </item>

        <item>
               "Started in 1555 and never completed, this Bastion took its name from San Michele's Church,
               which was later transfered in Via Etnea during the eighteenth-century.
               After 1693's earthquake the Bastion was exploited to create residences and was modified at the point
               it was unrecognizable: in fact, only a very small portion of the renaissance shoe wall remains in Via Coppola,
               where it remains part of an eighteenth-century building, Suca accessible only from the courtyard
               on the street number 43. The rest of the building is a elegant noble palace of the early
               twentieth century, now devoid of any element that reminds its original military function."
        </item>

        <item>
               "'Il Bastione degli Infetti' is the best preserved among the bastions that constituted
               the Etneo difensive system. Cicero tell in the Verrine that in the place where today are the remains
               of the bastion stood the Temple of Ceres, place of worship and pilgrimages.
               The name derives from the transformation of the Bastion into a lazaretto in 1576, because of the plague
               that hit the city of Catania."
        </item>

        <item>
               "Left unharmed by the eruption of 1669 it was partly destroyed by the earthquake that occurred in the same year,
               but it was the negligence and the degradation of the following centuries that definitively altered its physiognomy."
        </item>

        <item>
               "The Bastion Santa Croce costituted the external defense of the castle Ursino and was located east
               along the Gammazita curtain and was partly destroyed because of the 1669 eruption;
               it was armed with 2 pieces of artillery."
        </item>

        <item>
            "'Il Bastione del Tindaro' was initially part of the city's defensive system in the 16th century.
            It then became border of the benedectine's garden, who bought it to delimit the green area of their monastery.
            Today, all the rests of the Bastion are a few structures inside the Vittorio Emanuele Hospital
            and along the Tindaro alley.
            The Bastion took its name from the demolished church dedicated to the Madonna del Tindaro, which was
            demolished to make space for the Vittorio Emanuele Hospital and the Spedalieri high school."

         </item>

        <item>
                "'Il Bastione del Santo Carcere' was built in the 16th century to protect the Vetere,
                the city's first cathedral, linked by tradition to the places of martyrdom of S. Agata.
                After the earthquake in 1693, it was partly demolished to obtain the facade of the S. Agata al Carcere's church.
                Today, it is an obligatory stop for the Feast of S. Agata."

        </item>

        <item>
               "'La Porta di Carlo V' is the only gate among the sixteenth century walls of Charles V
                and remains intact at the Fishmonger's. Previously known as "Porta dei Canali",
                took its name from the homonym fountain on which it overlooked and is the only surviving gate.
                On top of it a marble plaque engraved in characters and Latin language expresses the
                desire of Charles V to equip the city of Catania with walls."
        </item>

        <item>
               "'La Porta della Decima' was also known as 'Porta Siracusa' and was born in sostitution
                of the ancient Porta Ariana. Its existence is confirmed in Middle Ages, as it is written
                in history books. The Gate took its name from the tithing ("Decima" in italian),
                a tax that forced the farmers to pay one-tenth of the harvest as a tribute to the king."
        </item>

        <item>
               "Also known as 'Porta de Verga' and rebuilt in 1553, it replaced
               a more ancient gate - La Porta del Porto - and took its name from the viceroy Juan de Vega to whom it was dedicated.
               In the eighteenth century it became a cause of discord between the archdiocese and the family Paternò Castello, both parts
               bordering the Porta and interested in his control. It was demolished during nineteenth century for the widening of the alley
               that reached the port, today known as Via del Porticello."

        </item>

        <item>
               "Born to guarantee an access to the city from the little
               Porto Aragonese, its uncertain location had to be not too far from the current Piazza Duca di Genova.
               It was demolished toghether with the stretch of walls on which it faced for the making of the new sixteenth century
               curtain which surrounded the Civita district."
        </item>

        <item>
                "This gate owes its name to the metal grille that closed it: according to the
                tradition, it was obtained with the loot of Tunis following the victory reported in 1535 by Charles V and Andrea Doria's
                fleet against the pirate Barbarossa."
        </item>

        <item>
               "This gate was previously called Porta Aquilonare. Thanks to his location on the aragonese-period walls,
               it became the privileged entrance to the city of the sovereigns of the Trinacria Kingdom,
               directly devoted to the ancient church of S.Agata la Vetere, first seat of the bishopric chair and traditionally
               seat of the tomb of the patroness of the city. The gate used to open where today is Via Santa Maddalena,
               right in front of Stanta Maria della Purità e della Visitazione's church."
        </item>

        <item>
               "Built in the 14th century on the stretch of walls to the northwest,
               where it's now located the Vittorio Emanuele II Hospital, it got destroyed by the 1669 cast,
               its name appears to be linked to the nearby Bastion."
        </item>

        <item>
               "Porta di Sant'Orsola, previously called 'Posterna Joenio', was opened in 1671. The gate was
               located near the church of S.Orsola, in the area of the current Piazza Scammacca, behind Teatro Massimo,
               and was demolished after the 1693 earthquake to trace the new roads of Catania."

        </item>

        <item>
               "Erected in the defensive system of the moat of Castello Ursino during the 16th century,
               it was also entirely demolished by the 1693 eruption. Its exact location is not
               yet clear, probably in the west zone of Piazza Federico II di Svevia."
        </item>

        <item>
               "Probably from Middle Age, it opened slight after Bastione di San Giovanni.
               Its destruction happened during the 1669 eruption, which cast came through this gate to stop several meters inside,
               close to Piazza Santi Cosma e Damiano, today called Piazza Niccolò Machiavelli."
        </item>

        <item>
               "Erected on the medieval wall in the west, in the stretch of Via Giuseppe Garibaldi which is at the
               crossroad with Via Plebiscito, it was rebuilt with the 16th-century fortification plan.
               Never completed, it was demolished in 1792 to expand Via Garibaldi. It owes its name to the fief or Sardinia,
               rich land in the west of the city."
        </item>

        <item>
                "There were two gates with this title: the first, of undefined age, was perhaps from the Aragonese age,
                opening to the walls of that period; the second one replaced it in the sicteenth century, erected not far behind
                and collapsed during the 1693 earthquake. The few rests were demolished for the extension of the Lanza road,
                that is now called Via Antonino di San Giuliano."
        </item>

        <item>
               "The city walls had several 'service' openings, called 'Postierle', usually not reported in the general plans as secondary accesses.
               However, thanks to some prints signed by Tiburzio Spannocchi who was entrusted with the supervision of the wall
               in view of their reformulation and strenghtening, we are able to identify with certainty at least one of them:
               Porta della Cunzaria, located near Bastione Grande,led to a tannery of skins that in the 16th century was located where today the Harbor Customs rises and that in the eighteenth century was adapted to lazzaretto, on a lava spur
               overlooking the sea."
        </item>

        <item>
               "Also knows as "Fontana de' setti caneddi", today it is located below a great arch,
               close to Palazzo dei Chierici, in a lower street level than Piazza Duomo as it was built before the earthquake.
               The original fountain of the 36 canals was placed along the walls opposite the gate and in the overlying part
               presented paintings depicting the story of the river god Amerano. It was destroyed by the eruption of 1669."
        </item>

        <item>
               "Lungo il tratto di mura che va dalla Porta di Carlo verso la marina in via Dusmet.
               Il nome deriva dalla sua collocazione, lungo la via Lanaria in onore al governatore
               Francesco Lanario Duca di Carpignano. La dedica a S. Agata è legata invece alla
               tradizione secondo la quale la fontana segna il punto da dove partirono le reliquie
               della Santa per Bisanzio per ordine del Generale Giorgio Maniace. A febbraio, festa
               della patrona S. Agata, il simulacro della santa percorre l’antico tratto delle mura;
               la fontana, in occasione della ricorrenza, e’ meta di pellegrinaggi dei devoti."Along the stretch of walls
        </item>

        <item>
               "Dopo il terremoto del 1693 il principe Ignazio Paterno’ Castello III, principe di Biscari,
               ottenne dal Luogotenente Generale Giuseppe Lanza, Duca di Camastra , il permesso di
               edificare un nuovo palazzo sul terrapieno delle mura cinquecentesche di Carlo V.
               I lavori di costruzione durarono più di un secolo e vi parteciparono i più grandi
               architetti catanesi dell’epoca: Alonzo di Benedetto, Girolamo Palazzotto,
               Francesco Battaglia. Fu realizzato il più sontuoso palazzo privato di Catania.
               La bellezza degli intagli e delle sculture non era solo frutto di gusto e di stile ma
               rifletteva la capacità tecnica e artistica delle Suca maestranze catanesi: la bravura degli
               intagliatori e decoratori conferiva alle opere notevole pregio artistico."
        </item>

        <item>
               "Il Palazzo fu costruito a pianta trapezoidale, accentrato su un grande cortile dove
               insisteva una scala centrale a tenaglia che introduceva nei ricchi saloni; raggiunse
               il massimo splendore nel 1700 sotto Ignazio V Principe di Biscari, grande viaggiatore
               ed appassionato di letteratura, d’arte, architettura e letteratura. Il Principe
               partecipò personalmente alla progettazione di nuove ale del Palazzo fornendo originali
               soluzioni costruttive."
        </item>

        <item>
               "Il Castello Ursino faceva parte di quella rete di fortificazioni lungo le coste
               dell’Italia meridionale e della Sicilia, voluta da Federico di Svevia, per un piano
               di edilizia militare; fu lo stesso Imperatore a scegliere il luogo di edificazione.
               Era circondato per tre lati dal mare e difeso da un poderoso muraglione. Dal XVI secolo,
               con l’introduzione della polvere da sparo, il castello vide sempre più indebolito il
               suo ruolo militare, diventando prigione. Fu investito e danneggiato dall’eruzione
               del 1669 ; la lava arrivò attorno al castello e, pur non intaccandone le strutture,
               colmò il fossato, coprì i bastioni e spostò per alcune centinaia di metri anche la
               linea di costa. Il terremoto del 1693 provocò una serie di danni alle strutture,
               compromettendo definitivamente il ruolo militare del castello. Negli anni 30’ del
               Novecento fu oggetto di un radicale restauro in vista della sua trasformazione in museo."
        </item>

        <item>
               "Fa parte della cinta muraria cinquecentesca e si trova nella zona sud-ovest del centro
               storico di Catania; collegava il Castello Ursino e la Porta di Carlo V. Le mura in
               questo tratto costeggiavano i ruderi di antiche fabbriche che prendevano il nome di
               “Muro rotto”. Nel Medioevo questa parte della città era la sede della Judecca Suttana,
               il quartiere ebraico, ed era piuttosto ricca di attività commerciali. Nel 1621 don
               Francesco Lanario, soprintendente generale alleSuca fortificazioni, nell’ambito di un
               generale restauro dell’assetto difensivo della città restaurò anche la zona della fonte.
               Le acque di Gammazita furono così imbrigliate e congiunte a quelle dell’Amenano.
               Nel 1669, a seguito dell’eruzione, la lava circondò il Castello Ursino, colmandone il
               fossato, e invase tutta l’area del quartiere ricoprendo anche le sorgenti, fra cui
               quella di Gammazita."
        </item>
    </string-array>

</resources>